Guide to the Robert E. Lucas Papers, 1960-2004 and undated RL.00826
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert E. Lucas papers
1960-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lucas, Robert E.
RL.00826
27 Linear Feet
0.12 Gigabytes
Robert E. Lucas is an Economist at the University of Chicago and Nobel Prize laureate. The Robert E. Lucas Papers span the years 1960-2004, and document the professional work and career of Lucas during his appointments at the Graduate School of Industrial Administration at Canegie-Mellon University, and at the Department of Economics at the University of Chicago. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Professional Service; Research Files; and Teaching Material, with the most substantial material in the research series. Folders assembled and maintained by Lucas over many years contain notes, correspondence, drafts, clippings, reports, course and departmental files, and other material related to topics such as business cycles, monetary theory, rational expectations, economic growth, supply-side economics, and unemployment.
Approximately 13,875 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. Access is by permission for the lifetime of the donor.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert E. Lucas Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2004.
Biographical Note
Robert Emerson Lucas Jr. was born September 15, 1937, in Yakima, Washington. He received his B.A. in History in 1959 and Ph.D. in Economics in 1964, both from the University of Chicago. He taught at the Graduate School of Industrial Administration at Carnegie-Mellon University from 1963 until 1975, when he returned to the University of Chicago. In 1980, he was named the John Dewey Distinguished Service Professor at University of Chicago. In 1995, he received the Nobel Memorial Prize in Economic Sciences for his work on macroeconomics.
Collection Overview
The Robert E. Lucas Papers span the years 1960-2004, and represent the professional work and career of Lucas during his appointments at the Graduate School of Industrial Administration at Canegie-Mellon University, and at the Department of Economics at the University of Chicago. The collection is arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Professional Service; Research Files; and Teaching Material. Lucas is best known for for having developed and applied the hypothesis of rational expectations, and thereby having transformed macroeconomic analysis and deepened the understanding of economic policy. His work in these and other areas is profiled in the Research Files Series, the most substantial of the collection. Folders assembled and maintained by Lucas over many years contain notes, correspondence, drafts, clippings, reports, and other material related to topics such as business cycles, monetary theory, rational expectations, economic growth, supply side economics, and unemployment. No less significant is the Correspondence Series, nine boxes of exchanges with such economists and colleagues such as Lucas' collaborators Edward C. Prescott and Thomas Sargent, as well as James Tobin, Neil Wallace, Karl Brunner, David Cass, Edmund S. Phelps, Robert J. Gordon, Robert J. Barro, Leonard A. Rapping and John B. Taylor. These letters amplify the documentation in the research files on Lucas' career and research, as well as topics and debates in economics in the 20th century.
In addition to documenting Lucas' work in theoretical economics, the collection also follows his professional activities through documents found in the Professional Service Series. Items relate to his participation on various committees, his editorial and presidential commitments, and his work with institutions such as the American Economic Association (AEA), the National Science Foundation (NSF), and the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER).
Finally, the Teaching Material Series, offers administrative files and course materials, such as notes, transparencies and exam subjects, dating from the 1960s to the 1990s and relating to Lucas' academic departmental service and teaching career.
Detailed descriptions on the arrangement and content of each series can be found in the respective sections of this collection guide.
Keynesian economics; Macroeconomics; Monetary policy; Rational expectations (Economic theory); Business cycles; Economists -- Correspondence; Economists -- United States; Fiscal policy; Unemployment; Supply-side economics; Wallace, Neil; Phelps, Edmund S.; Lucas, Robert E.; Rapping, Leonard A.; Prescott, Edward C.; Taylor, John B.; Sargent, Thomas J.; University of Chicago. Dept. of Economics; Tobin, James, 1918-2002; Barro, Robert J.; Brunner, Karl, 1916-1989; Gordon, Robert J. (Robert James), 1940-; Carnegie-Mellon University. Graduate School of Industrial Administration; Cass, David
- Correspondence Series, 1963-1998, 9 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This correspondence series is predominantly constituted by letters between Lucas and his colleagues on research issues. With the exception of the final box, all the correspondence was filed by Lucas by year. Letters are grouped by month within each individual folder; however, further processing is need to organize them into complete chronological order.
  - Correspondence by date, 1963-1998
    Constituted by Lucas' exchanges with professional colleagues on research matters, including comments on the work of other economists, debates on current issues, recommendations and advising exchanges. Among his most frequent correspondents are his collaborators Edward C. Prescott and Thomas Sargent, from the early days at the Graduate School of Industrial Administration at Carnegie-Mellon University (1963-1974), to the most recent years at the Department of Economics of the University of Chicago (1990s). Major twentieth-century economists such as James Tobin, Neil Wallace, Karl Brunner, David Cass, Edmund S. Phelps, Robert J. Gordon, Robert J. Barro, Leonard A. Rapping and John B. Taylor, among others, are represented by smaller amounts of correspondence. This subseries, then, is a rich source of information that contains a very large amount of material written by and received by Lucas throughout his career. Chronologically filed by Lucas by year.
    - 1963-1968, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - 1969-1971, 4 folders (Box 1A)
    - 1972-1975, 7 folders (Box 2)
    - 1976-1978, 8 folders (Box 3)
    - 1979-1981, 9 folders (Box 4)
    - 1982-1984, 6 folders (Box 5)
    - 1985-1987, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - 1987-1988, 5 folders (Box 6A)
    - 1989-1992, 10 folders (Box 7)
    - 1993-1995, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - 1996-1998, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - 1999-2004, 6 folders Contains digital media: 1 CD-R. (Box 39)
    - 2006-2011, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - undated (Box 39)
  - Correspondence by subject, 1976-1989
    Brief subseries that includes correspondence on specific subjects, much of it routine, which Lucas filed separately from his general correspondence files. Arranged in alphabetical order by last name or subject.
    - Meunich, Polemarchis and Weiss, 1976 (Box 9)
    - Requests and visits to give lectures, 1976-1986 (Box 9)
    - Taxes correspondence, 1989 (Box 9)
- Professional Service Series, 1971-2004, 3 boxes
  Contains materials concerning Lucas' connections to organisations involved with both the direction and funding of the discipline, and to other professional associations. Includes budget and committee meetings, correspondence, editorial and presidential duties, conference proceedings, and peer reviews written by Lucas for journal submissions. Arranged in alphabetical order by last name or subject.
  - American Economic Association (AEA) Commission on Graduate Education, 1991 (Box 10)
  - AEA, Committee and budget report, 2001-2003, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - AEA, Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - AEA, Executive committee on the status of Minorities in the Economics Profession, 1981 (Box 39)
  - AEA, Journal of Political Economy editorship, 2001-2002 (Box 10)
  - AEA, Meeting, 2002 (Box 10)
  - AEA, Meeting, unemployment, 1977 (Box 10)
  - AEA, Papers and Proceedings Committee, 2007 (Box 39)
  - AEA, Presidential address, 2001-2002, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - AEA, Presidential reception, 2002-2003 (Box 10)
  - AEA, Statistics committee, 2002 (Box 11)
  - AEA, Status of women in the profession, 2001-2003 (Box 11)
  - Association of Chinese-American Scientists and Engineers, 1999-2009 (Box 39)
  - Bank of Sweden Prize, 1999-2009 (Box 39)
  - Bureau of the Budget, 1966-1967 (Box 39)
  - Econometric Society, 1990, 1997-1998 (Box 11)
  - Econometric Society, 2000 World Congress, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Historical Society, 2002 (Box 11)
  - Journal of Economic Theory, 1971-1978, 5 folders (Box 11)
  - Mitchell Hutchins conference, 1977, 1977-1979 (Box 39)
  - Modigliani Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 39)
  - National Academy of Sciences, 1981-1982, 2004, undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - National Science Foundation, 1981 (Box 12)
  - NSF panel, 1974-1975, 5 folders (Box 40)
  - NSF proposals, 1975-1979, 3 folders (Box 40, Box 12)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research conference, 1981 (Box 12)
  - NU workshop, 1994 (Box 41)
  - Personal professional files, 1975-2010 (Box 41)
  - Review of papers for journals, 1971-1979, 4 folders (Box 12)
  - Tobin venture - National Association for Business Economics, 1976-1986, 2 folders (Box 12)
- Research Files Series, 1960-2000 and undated, 16 boxes
  Contains extensive documentation related to Lucas' research and to the writing of his articles, papers, or book-length works. The series is divided into ten subseries that describe the wide range of Lucas' research and which are listed alphabetically: Business Cycles, Growth and Development, International Economics, Investment, Labor and Unemployment, Miscellaneous Subject Files, Monetary Theory, Prices, Rational Expectations, and Supply-Side Economics. It includes drafts, notes, comments and different versions of Lucas' papers, articles and books, with emphasis on monetary theory, business cycles and growth. Overall, the subseries is further enhanced by the frequent presence of related correspondence between Lucas and his co-authors or commentators, as well as printed materials (such as reports, clippings, reprints and journal articles) and writings by others, both published and unpublished, related to Lucas' research.
  - Business Cycles
    - An equilibrium model of the business cycle, 1974 (Box 13)
    - Barro, Robert, 1974, 2000, undated (Box 13)
    - Business cycle modeling, 1970s (Box 13)
    - Cycle notes, 1994 (Box 13)
    - Directions of macroeconomics, 1979 (Box 13)
    - Equilibrium cycle, undated (Box 13)
    - Lecture notes, 1979-1980 (Box 13)
    - Linear economy, undated (Box 13)
    - Lucas problem, undated (Box 13)
    - Methods and problems in business cycle theory, 1980 (Box 13)
    - Models of business cycles, 1985-1987 (Box 13)
    - Output inflation tradeoffs, 1973 (Box 14)
    - Studies in business cycles, undated (Box 14)
    - Time to build, 1980-1981 (Box 14)
    - Understanding business cycles, 1976-1979, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Various articles, 1980s (Box 14)
  - Growth and Development
    - Capital flow from rich to poor countries, 1989-1990, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Development drafts, undated (Box 14)
    - Human capital, 1990, undated, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Idea Flows, Economic Growth, and Trade, 2012 (Box 41)
    - Knowledge Growth and the Allocation of Time, 2011, 2 folders (Box 41)
    - Learning and growth, undated (Box 14)
    - Making a miracle, 1991-1993, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Optimal growth with many consumers, 1982, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - On the mechanics of economic development, 1985-1988, 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Rosen proposal, undated (Box 15)
    - Sources of growth, 1990 (Box 15)
    - Substitution and growth, 1975 (Box 15)
    - Towards full employment and price stability, 1978 (Box 16)
    - Trade and the Diffusion of the Industrial Revolution, 2008 (Box 41)
    - What Was the Industrial Revolution?, 2007 (Box 41)
    - World development indicators, 1983 (Box 16)
    - World development report, 1991, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - World real interest rates, 1990 (Box 16)
  - International Economics
    - Asian financial crisis, 1999 (Box 16)
    - Exchange rate regimes, 1980 (Box 16)
    - Floating exchange rates, 1988 (Box 16)
    - Interest rates and currency prices in a two-country world, 1980s, 1 of 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Interest rates and currency prices in a two-country world, 1980s, 2-3 of 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Trade, undated (Box 17)
  - Investment
    - Distributed lags and optimal investment policy, 1965 (Box 17)
    - Firm size, 1970s (Box 17)
    - Investment under uncertainty, 1968-1969 (Box 17)
    - On the size distribution of business firms, 1977-1978, 3 folders (Box 17)
  - Labor and Unemployment
    - Equilibrium search and employment, 1970s (Box 18)
    - Expectations and the neutrality of money, 1969-1970 (Box 18)
    - International evidence of output-inflation trade off, undated (Box 18)
    - Labour supply, undated, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Real wages, employment and inflation, 1960s (Box 18)
    - Towards full employment and price stability, 1970s (Box 18)
    - Unemployment insurance, 1990s, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Unemployment policy, undated (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous Subject Files
    - After Keynesian macroeconomics, 1977-1978, 3 folders (Box 19)
    - Capacity, overtime and investment, 1969 (Box 19)
    - Core, 1980 (Box 19)
    - Costs of inflation, 1981 (Box 19)
    - Crisis, 2009 (Box 42)
    - Development, undated (Box 19A)
    - Dominant firm model, 1966 (Box 19A)
    - Drafts, undated (Box 19A)
    - Duality, undated (Box 19A)
    - Dynamic competitive analysis, 1977 (Box 19A)
    - Edward Prescott papers, 1974-1976 (Box 42)
    - Efficient allocations, 1990 (Box 19A)
    - Efficient distribution, 1991 (Box 20)
    - Equilibrium search and unemployment, 1973 (Box 20)
    - Goldberg Appeal, 1997 (Box 42)
    - Inflation and price controls, 1974 (Box 20)
    - Internal structure of cities, 1999-2012 (Box 42)
    - Japan--Money, 2 folders (Box 42)
    - Letters, 1960-1970 (Box 20)
    - Loose papers, 1976-1977, 1992 (Box 20)
    - Lucas-Prescott monograph, undated (Box 20)
    - Matching, 1975 (Box 20)
    - Menu costs and Phillips curves, 2005, 3 folders (Box 42)
    - MIT notes, 1978 (Box 20)
    - Notes, 1970s, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Notes on the Leiderman workshop, 1988 (Box 20)
    - NY Times columns, 1981 (Box 20)
    - Optimal policy, 1982 (Box 21)
    - Price systems, 1970s (Box 21)
    - Principles of fiscal and monetary policy, 1984-1985 (Box 21)
    - Random earnings differences, 1990-1991 (Box 21)
    - Recursive competitive equilibrium, 1982 (Box 21)
    - Review of Skidelsdy volumes on Keynes, 1994 (Box 21)
    - Rules, discretion and the role of the economic advisor, 1978 (Box 21)
    - Scalator clauses, 1976-1977 (Box 22)
    - Schoonmaker, 1968 (Box 22)
    - Stanford, 1976 (Box 22)
    - Thesis topics, 1977 (Box 22)
    - Weiss problem, 1983 (Box 22)
  - Monetary Theory
    - Carnegie-Mellon notes, 1976 (Box 22)
    - Cash-in-advance economy, 1976 (Box 22)
    - Collected papers on Monetary Theory, 2011 (Box 43)
    - Columbia notes, 1978 (Box 22)
    - Diamond inefficiency, 1977 (Box 22)
    - Equilibrium in a pure currency economy, 1978, 3 folders (Box 22)
    - Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis, 1996-1997 (Box 22)
    - Fluctuations, 1981 (Box 23)
    - Historical quantity of money, undated (Box 23)
    - Labor hoarding, 1988 (Box 23)
    - Liquidity and interest rates, 1988, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Liquidity effect, 1981 (Box 23)
    - Management conference, 1979 (Box 23)
    - Money demand in the U.S., 1987-1989 (Box 23)
    - Monetary shocks with prices set in advance, 1989-1990 (Box 23)
    - Monetary transmission mechanism, 1983 (Box 23)
    - Money, 1975-1977, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Money and finance, 1983 (Box 24)
    - Money in a theory of finance, 1983 (Box 24)
    - Note on Wallace reformulation, liquity and interest rates, 1988 (Box 24)
    - Notes on monetary theory, 1977, 4 folders (Box 24)
    - On the Stability of Money Demand, 2011 (Box 43)
    - Open market, 1980s (Box 24)
    - Optimal fiscal and monetary policy, 1983 (Box 24)
    - Price fixing, 1979 (Box 24)
    - Project on monetary design, 1980 (Box 25)
    - Quantity theory of money, 1978-1980, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Real effects of monetary shocks, 1992-1994, 4 folders (Box 25)
    - Reflections on contemporary macroeconomics, 1980, 1 of 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Reflections on contemporary macroeconomics, 1980, 2 of 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Topics on monetary theory, 1990 (Box 26)
    - Transactions, 1988 (Box 26)
    - Two illustrations of the quantity theory of money, 1979 (Box 26)
  - Prices
    - A note on price systems in infinite dimensional space, 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Asset prices, 1989 (Box 26)
    - Asset prices in an exchange economy, 1970s (Box 26)
    - Fixing prices, 1990 (Box 26)
    - Price fixing, 1979, 1 of 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Price fixing, 1979, 2 of 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Rational Expectations
    - Adaptive behavior, 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Budget balance, 1977 (Box 27)
    - Economic practice, 1979 (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 1974 (Box 27)
    - Optimal investment with rational expectations, 1968 (Box 27)
    - Santa Clara symposium, 1979-1980 (Box 27)
    - UCLA, 1980 (Box 27)
  - Supply-Side Economics
    - Efficient allocation, 1990s (Box 28)
    - Efficiency and equality in a simple model of efficient unemployment insurance, 1993 (Box 28)
    - On efficiency and distribution, 1991 (Box 28)
    - On efficiency and distribution with private information, 1992 (Box 28)
    - Supply side economics, 1990 (Box 28)
    - Supply side economics: an analytical review, 1989 (Box 28)
    - Taxes calculations, 1989 (Box 28)
    - Taxes notes, 1989 (Box 28)
  - Oversize Material
    - Financial sections, Christian Science Monitor, 1977 April, 5 items (Box 28, Folder 1)
- Teaching Materials Series, 1965-circa 1999 and undated, 10 boxes
  The Administrative Files Subseries chiefly contains letters of recommendation and of reference and general reports related to departmental affairs. In the second subseries, course materials chiefly consist of course notes, transparencies, comments on students' work and exam subjects. Arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Administrative Files Subseries, 1965-circa 1999 and undated
    - Budget committee report, 1969 (Box 29)
    - Budget data - Carnegie-Mellon, 1968-1970, 2 folders (Box 29)
    - Budget general, 1969 (Box 29)
    - Budget report 1965-1969, 1968-1969 (Box 29)
    - Center for Advanced Studies in Economics and Quantitative Methods, proposals, undated (Box 43)
    - Committee on academic tenure, 1971-1972 (Box 29)
    - Committee on Departmental Admin, 1984 (Box 43)
    - Dean search committee, 2006 (Box 43)
    - Department budget data, 1986-1988 (Box 43)
    - Departmental matters, 1975-1983, 1-4 of 5 folders (Box 29)
    - Departmental matters, 1975-1983, 5 of 5 folders (Box 30)
    - Earhart Foundation, 1974 (Box 30)
    - Economics at Chicago, 1975-1977 (Box 30)
    - Edward C. Prescott, 1982 (Box 30)
    - Faculty business, 1978-1980 (Box 43)
    - Harberger party, 1991 (Box 30)
    - Letters of recommendation, 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Letters of reference, 1967-1974 (Box 30)
    - Macro syllabus, 1994 (Box 30)
    - Policy committee, undated, 1 of 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Policy committe, undated, 2 of 2 folders (Box 31)
    - Recruiting 2000, circa 1999 (Box 31)
    - Rosen committee, 1980-1981 (Box 43)
    - Space, 1979 (Box 31)
    - Teaching evaluation, 1972 (Box 31)
    - Tuition data, 1973 (Box 31)
    - Tuition changes, undated, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - UC committee, undated (Box 31)
  - Course Materials Subseries, 1965-1998 and undated
    - 1986-1987 (Box 43)
    - Advanced economic analysis, 1969-1970 and 2000 (Box 31)
    - Advanced theoretical economics, 1986-1993 (Box 31)
    - Applied econometrics, 1974 (Box 31)
    - Capital theory, 1997-1998, 2 folders (Box 31)
    - Case studies in economic development, 1983 (Box 43)
    - Control problems, 1994 (Box 32)
    - CORE exams, 1989-1996 (Box 43)
    - Dynamic systems sets, 1982-1985 (Box 32)
    - ECON 335 and 337, 1977-1993 (Box 43)
    - Economic development, 1984 (Box 32)
    - Economic growth, 1980 (Box 32)
    - Empirical growth, 1977-1978 (Box 32)
    - Equilibrium dynamics, 1991-1992, 2 folders (Box 32)
    - Fifth semester exam, 1970 (Box 32)
    - Fiscal, money and macro, 1990 (Box 32)
    - Fiscal and monetary policy, 1997 (Box 32)
    - G. Brenner notes, 1978 (Box 32)
    - Graduate student papers, 1979-1990, 9 of 13 folders (Box 33)
    - Graduate student papers, 1996-1998, 10-13 of 13 folders (Box 34)
    - Income, 1991-1995 and 1997, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Income, asset pricing, 1990-1994 (Box 34)
    - Income, macro, 1997-1998 (Box 35)
    - Income, macro development, 1984-1988 (Box 35)
    - International trade and economic growth, 2001-2009, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Labor markets, 1978-1984 (Box 35)
    - Linear dynamics, 1977-1982 (Box 35)
    - Macro, 1989-2000, 4 folders; 3 folders (Box 44, Box 35)
    - Macro problems, 1977-1979 and undated (Box 35)
    - Macro problems and draft textbook, 1967-1973 and undated (Box 36)
    - Mathematics for economics, 1979-1993 and undated (Box 44)
    - Markov process probability, 1993 (Box 36)
    - Mathematical economics, 1971-1973 (Box 36)
    - Mathematical review, 1970 (Box 36)
    - Micro, macro, 1969 (Box 36)
    - Miscellaneous topics, 1995-1996 (Box 36)
    - Monetary theory, 1978-1981 and 1983, 2 folders (Box 36)
    - Money and banking, 1990-1994, 1-2 of 3 folders (Box 36)
    - Money and banking, 1990-1994, 3 of 3 folders (Box 37)
    - N-agent planning problem, 1997 (Box 37)
    - Neoclassical growth, 1976-1981 (Box 37)
    - Overhead for projector, undated (Box 37)
    - Price theory, 1972-1973 (Box 37)
    - Probability, 1995 and 1998 (Box 37)
    - Probability lecture notes, 1965 (Box 37)
    - Problem tests, 1976 and 1984 (Box 37)
    - Public finance, 1991 (Box 37)
    - Reading lists, 1975-1983 (Box 38)
    - Resource allocation, 1968 (Box 38)
    - Recursive methods, undated (Box 38)
    - Special topics in monetary theory, 1989 (Box 38)
    - Student papers, 1984 and undated, 2 folders (Box 38)
    - Syllabi, 1983-1984 (Box 38)
    - Theory of income, 2001 (Box 44)
    - Time series problem, 1978 (Box 38)
    - Topics in international trade, 2003 (Box 44)
    - Trade and growth, 1979-1984 (Box 38)
    - Trade and growth, public finance, 1978-1981 (Box 38)
- Oversize Material
  - Clippings (Oversize-folder 1)
- Digital Material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Electronic records in this series have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.